<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some considerations offered to the Honourable House of Commons against a bill depending about transportation of wooll</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1669</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60779</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4492B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26247</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09402707</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09402707</idno>
            <idno type="VID">42977</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60779)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42977)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1315:28)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some considerations offered to the Honourable House of Commons against a bill depending about transportation of wooll</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 broadside.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1669]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Wool industry --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Wool industry --  Law and legislation --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-03</date>
            <label>Elspeth Healey</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:42977:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 15 -->
            <head>SOME CONSIDERATIONS Offered to the Honourable <hi>Houſe of Commons</hi> againſt a Bill depending about <hi>Transportation of VVooll.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WHereas there is a Bill depending, the Preamble whereof ſeems to be againſt Tranſportation of Wooll, the Scope and Conſequence of it (as is humbly conceived) will tend rather to encourage it: For whereas it is ſuggeſted in the ſaid Bill, that the Act made in the 14th. Year of His Majeſties Reign, making Tranſporting of Wooll Felony, is ineffectual for the preventing thereof, and therefore prays the Repeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Felony of that Act, without confirming the reſt of that Act; as if making Tranſportation to be Felony did encourage Tranſporting; that Suggeſtion with all ſubmiſſion is conceived to be a great miſtake: For though it muſt be granted (whatever Laws have been or ſhall be made in this caſe) that ſome Perſons for their own Lucre (though it be never ſo much to the Damage of the great Manufacture of this Kingdom, and notwithſtanding all the Care imaginable) will adventure to tranſport Wooll. Yet for ſome Years after that Act of the 14 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. was in force, there was a great ſtop put to the ſaid Tranſportation, untill Wooll ſo increaſed in <hi>Ireland</hi> beyond its Conſumption there and here, that Great Quantities were actually tranſported from thence; but till that Glut the Act of the 12th. Year of His Majeſties Reign (by which the Forfeiture was Three Shillings for every Pound of Wooll, beſides the Wooll forfeited) conjoyned with the Act in the 14th. Year of His Majeſties Reign, was found effectual to prohibit Tranſporting Wooll, for the Proſecutor had liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to proſecute upon which Act he pleaſed as to the Forfeiture; and therefore there was not one Perſon in twenty proſecuted upon the Penalty of what was proſecuted on the Forfeiture of Three Shillings <hi>per</hi> Pound, that of Felony ſerving onely to make Offenders afraid, but thoſe Acts of the 12th. and 14th. were in this found defective, that they did not ſufficiently provide how to make good Proof of an Intention to Tranſport when Wooll was brought near the Sea-ſide: So that both Acts together, as the Forfeiture now ſtands (ſaving the defects aforeſaid, and want of putting the Laws in execution) are far better as they are than with this new intended Alteration, as is found in Ten Years Experience, by thoſe who have made it their whole buſineſs to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend this Affair, if thoſe Perſons principally concerned in point of Intereſt may be ſuppoſed capable of Judging; or thoſe who have made it their buſineſs not onely to inſpect it, but to keep a conſtant Correſpondency about this matter beyond the Seas, and who for ſome Years have been partly at Sea, and partly on the Ssacoaſts, to make Discoveries, and who afterwards have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted thoſe Diſcoveries, ſome in the Exchequer, others at the Aſſizes, to the number at the leaſt of One hundred Perſons, who have been found guilty of Tranſporting Wooll contrary to thoſe Acts, but many of them eſcaped the Penalties by the late gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Act of Pardon.</p>
            <p>And upon Complaint made about Ten Years ſince to His Majeſty and Council, (who were very apprehenſive of this Miſchief, and willing by all lawful ways imaginable to prevent it) of ſome Negligence and Remiſneſs of Officers and others, it was refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by His Majeſty and Council to the Council for Trade, which Council for Trade making Report to the Board, His Majeſty and Council paſſed this Opinion following.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="document">
                        <opener>
                           <dateline>At the Court at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> 
                              <date>April 1669.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>WHereas in purſuance of an Order of this Board of the 20th. of <hi>November</hi> last, referring to the Council for Trade the Propoſals of <hi>William Carter,</hi> for preventing the Exportation of Wooll and conveying thereof beyond the Seas, the ſaid Council have returned their Report to the Board, that having diſcourſed with the ſaid <hi>William Carter,</hi> and ſuch other perſons as they thought capable of giving them any good Information touching this matter, they find the Exportation of Wooll is of a deſtructive conſequence to the Trade of this Kingdom, and that the ſame, hath grown into Practice as well by reaſon of the doubtfulneſs of ſome Expreſſions in the Statute made in the 12th. Year of His Majeſties Reign, prohibiting the Exportation of Wooll, as by the neglect and remiſneſs of Officers in not putting the Laws in due execution.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Whereupon the late Lord Keeper <hi>Bridgman,</hi> being then in Council, prepared a Bill, and at the Opening of the next Seſſion of Parliament cauſed it to be read in the Houſe of Lords, and when it was committed, ſeveral Merchants and Staplers in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> and alſo Clothiers were ſummoned, and did often attend the Lords of the Committee, where two Judges were conſtantly preſent to draw up Amendments to that Bill, which took up at leaſt 6 or 8 days at the Committee, and when the ſaid Bill was reported and engroſſed, by means of one Clauſe in that Bill, <hi>To burn the Ship wherein was found any Wooll,</hi>that Bill was at laſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected by the Lords; and afterwards the ſubſtance of that Bill in anothor Seſſion was put into the Houſe of Lords without the Clauſe of <hi>Burning the Ship,</hi> and was engroſſed and ſent down to the Commons, and then committed, but miſcarried alſo; and inſtead thereof the Bill now depending comes in, no ways approved of by the ſaid Merchants and Clothiers, becauſe inſtead of prohibiting it will be found in Expericnce to be the occaſion of Tranſporting much Wooll: Therefore before this Bill paſs, the ſaid Merchants and Clothiers pray they may be heard, who queſtion not but to give ſatisfaction to this Honourable Houſe of the great Inconvenience thereof.</p>
            <p>And further, the Bill now depending does propound to reſtrain Exporting, but by increaſing the Number of Ports in <hi>Ireland</hi> to have leave to Export; and by increaſing alſo the Number, of Ports in <hi>England</hi> where Wooll may be Imported, this Bill in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of reſtraining muſt needs give much more liberty to Tranſport than ever. So that now it will be utterly impoſſible to prevent Tranſportation of Wooll, becauſe where Wooll is ſuſpected and known to be Exported, it ſhall be pretended to be Imported, and very fairly coloured by this Bill.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
